[Music]
welcome my name is baj Koto I work as a
product manager in Microsoft Development
Center Copenhagen where we develop
business Central and we also develop a
mobile app for business centr
today we will be talking about uh the
mobile app and its new capabilities
including barcode
scanning announcing right now in October
2023 we have released the new version of
our mobile app this is version 4 4.0
available of course for um IOS and
Android supports new versions of those
operating systems and has some changes
and then of course new features which we
will be talking about about uh right now
this app is Backward Compatible so you
can download it from the store and U
used on your devices even if you are
connecting to previous version of
business Central or even if you are
working with business Central on
premises but of course to get the most
out of it uh you would need business
Central 2023 Wave 2 and of course after
you download the app please give give us
a good
rating first feature that I would like
to mention in that mobile app is tell me
the support for tell me on mobile the
alt Q keyboard shortcut is probably one
of the most popular on desktop and right
now this feature is coming to Mobile in
order to enable that feature you have to
go to feature management and turn it on
and of course if you have a new
environment like for instance the
preview sandbox this will be turned on
uh By You By by default it Supports
phone tablet devices various you know
landscape and portrait modes and of
course it works in the same way as tell
me works on desktop you can search for
any page report and then of course if
the user has uh enough permissions to go
and navigate to that page uh it will it
will work it also supports the keyboard
shortcut actually the alt Q keyboard
shortcut so if you have a mobile device
like for instance a tablet with a
keyboard it will also work with alt Q
next one is the search for data so this
feature search for data is enabled on
desktop within tell me and we have done
the same for mobile so right now if you
are running a mobile device you can
search for data from that tell me
experience from that search experience
on mobile and it works in the same way
uh it uses the same scoping for data
data that is available for the use for
the specific user but it can be also Al
configured by the administrator to
access specific tables so the
administrator is doing that on desktop
and the user logging from mobile device
will have the same experience or the
same access as uh doing that from
desktop and then of course permissions
are also honored in the same way this
feature also needs to be enabled in
feature management together with tel me
that is uh relatively uh
straightforward next thing is something
that is coming soon and that is support
for worksheet pages on mobile phones
specifically you have probably seen that
if you navigate to a page of type
worksheet those worksheet pages are
defined in a more complex way usually
they are meant to enter data in this
kind of excel like format so they didn't
really work nicely on mobile phones and
previously you will see a you would see
an an error message saying that
unfortunately this type of an experience
is not available on a phone and you need
to navigate you need to go and switch to
a tablet or desktop coming in version
23.1 so not right now in October but a
little bit later in November time frame
uh this type of experience will also be
available on mobile phone and it will
work in the same way as currently uh
document pages so you will have an an a
header and a footer and the lines and
then you will navigate through the those
lines and edit one by one so it's a
slightly different experience as to
desktop but uh most importantly those uh
worksheet pages will be available on
phone uh finally and we're welcoming
this change and I'm hoping that you also
will be happy with this with this change
coming later this wave but the most
important thing or most fun thing about
this new mobile app is the support for
barcode scanning to demonstrate that and
talk about that in detail I would
welcome my colleagues from the
engineering team clao and kasim thank
you blazes I'm clao I'm part of the
software engineering team here working
on business Central in Copenhagen and
today I'm joined by my colleague kasim
hi I'm kasim and I also work in the
application team based in Denmark as
well yeah so as my colleague has
previously mentioned uh we are bringing
some new features to the mobile app in
this wave um and the ones that I'm the
one I'm going to be focusing on is the
barcode scanning feature we believe that
that by bringing this new feature in the
application we will increase the overall
ux ux experience of the application but
also improve the user
productivity so therefore we now in the
new mobile application we support native
barcode scanning that can be enabled via
the AL language uh it works on all
supported phones tablets via camera it
it uses native mobile capabilities which
means that is actually using um software
specific um machine learning software
specific for actually detecting the
barcodes and then we are also bringing a
third integration uh for the barcode
scanning capability and that is we have
integrated uh dedicated barcode scanning
devices with business
Central in terms of the supported
barcode types out of the box support we
do support most of the well 1D 2D
barcode formats and probably the most
important thing uh we do support QR
codes as well because we do know that
our partners have actually asked for
this specific thing so yes we do support
QR codes as well uh for the native
Barcode Scanner support we have come up
with three scenarios H which are the
following we've added a new button in
the UI that involes the camera scanning
capability so basically when a user Taps
on this button the camera is going to be
invoked and uh therefore he will going
to be able to he's going to be able to
scan the barcode which in turn is going
to be sent to process to Al then
secondly we wanted we want to add more
flexibility to Al uh developers so we
allow them to actually um integrate with
camera scanning capabilities via an Alx
sensibility and the third one as I
mentioned we are integrating in this new
mobile app release with dedicated bar
Cod scanner devices however with the
caveat we only support devices that are
running on Android
OS for this first scenario we are
introducing a new capability to add an
action via Al which is going to project
um or render something on the string
something like the one that you see on
the slides um an icon with a barcode
scanner inside icon that when you user
tabs that actually the camera barcod
scanning capability will be invoked in
order to do so it's quite easy to
actually have this new capability all
you need to do is actually annotate
annotate a field of type code and text
with the extended data type property
equals barcode as soon as an Al
developer does that it will instruct the
mobile client to show the barcode
scanning capability uh when the page is
rendered on the supported
device secondly as I said we wanted to
actually bring some more flexibility and
give some more flexibility to Al
developers um so they can actually use
the new barcode scanning capability via
Al and integrate with it uh for example
not only that they can actually use it
next to a field but it can also also
enable the the the capability by um by a
r Center queue an action a button a link
or some automated Logic for instance
when a page is open and of course once
this barcode is actually scanned there
is returned the data is returned to Al
for further
processing and now my colleague aim is
actually going to demonstrate you how we
integrated this in the uh new business
Central application thank you cloria so
I will demonstrate this barcode
functionality by doing an endtoend
scenario inside business Central and
we'll show you how we have along the way
I will show you how we have integrated
the barcode features inside different
business processes inside business
Central so start by creating an item
then we will try to produce that item
and finally we will try to sell this
item so let's start so the first thing I
will go is to see the item itself so I
have created this item called coffee
beans and there are few things I want to
mention about this item that I have
created uh the first thing is the GTI in
number I've defined this number which is
which can be used to uniquely identify
this item and barcode scanners can use
this to either track or identify this
particular item and now we also have
this feature to print the label for this
uh GTI number for this particular item
and once I do that let's see how the
label itself looks like so this is the
label once I press print looks like this
is a word report and like cloria
mentioned there are a lot of formats
that we support but for this demo I've
used the standard on Dimension barcode
and Ive also used the QR code so now we
can actually print this uh label as well
and one more thing that I want to show
about this item is the item
references so the GTI number basically
identify the item uniquely but to
identify the variance of that item we
use the item references so over here you
can see we have a new reference type
called barcode and using this we can
identify each uh type of uh coffee beans
in our case it could be either a box of
coffee beans or a pack of coffee beans
we can also identify the validity of
these reference number by specifying the
starting and end date so let's say this
box reference item is only valid for a
week so similarly like GTI number we can
use the print label action to actually
print the uh reference number labels as
well and you can see now we have printed
two reference number labels one for uh
pack of coffee beans and the other is
for the box of coffee beans so now we
have an item for which we have
identified the GTI number and we we have
couple of reference number and we have
also specify the item tracking
information for this so let's try to
produce some of these item so I will go
to the assembly
orders and over here you can see I'm
trying to produce five coffee beans five
packs of coffee beans and I've specified
the location and and the bin where this
will be located and I've assigned the
resource to it so now I will go to the
item tracking lines for this assembly
order
um by using the assigned serial number
action I can create five serial numbers
for these five coffee beans that we are
going to produce so now I have created
these five serial numbers for five
coffee beans packs that we are going to
create now if I go to the serial number
information card page I have the option
to actually print the label for the
serial numbers so for all of these five
items that we create we can place the
serial number on each individual which
will uniquely identify each uh coffee
beans back so let's try to print the
labels for these seral numbers as
well so uh similar like GTI number and
reference number we have five barcode uh
tags for uh serial number as well so now
we have created the serial number for
these five items coffee beans that we
are going to create now we can actually
post this assembly order and we will
produce the five uh coffee beans so
let's go and
post while this posting is going on just
to summarize what we have done so far we
have identified the GTI number for the
items we have identified a few reference
numbers for the item in the end we have
created and produced five coffee beans
so let's assume I'm a warehouse employer
right now so what we have done so far is
create five packs of coffee beans so it
looks something like this and we have
the serial number uh barcode printed in
the front and we have the GTI number and
the reference number printed on the back
side so let's open the business Central
app in the tablet and see how the
warehouse employee might interact with
uh this barod features so the first
thing that you might see in the
warehouse uh worker role Center is two
new actions one is called the item
inquiry and the second is called item
bin content inquiry both of these
actions allows us to scan the barcode
and either get the details about the
item or get the details about the item
in a particular bin so let's try the
item bin content
inquiry so over here you can see there
is this icon for barcode uh and this is
uh just by defining the uh extended data
type as barcode and it automatically uh
picks it up over here the barcode could
be either gtin number or the reference
number of the item itself so let's try
to scan the reference
number I will press this icon and as
soon as I scan the reference number the
bin content has been opened and I can
see I have like 15 quantity of this uh
coffee beans inside
silver so now let's try to sell some of
these so I will go to the sales order
create a new sales
order specify the customer that we are
going to sell
this and on the line again you have the
option to select the item either from
the drop down or you can use this
barcode icon to scan the reference
number so let's scan the reference
number again for this coffee beans and
you can see it automatically fills the
line and it also knows like which type
of reference number I have attached so
it's uh this for this demo it's like the
pack so let's try to sell three coffee
beans
pack and we need to identify the
location as well because it was in
silver location so let's go to the item
tracking lines for this
line over here you can see I could
either scan each individual uh pack of
coffee beans from the line itself or I
could use the uh action called scan
multiple which will allow me to continue
scanning so since we have more than one
item so I will use the scan
multiple and we are going to scan serial
numbers so I'm going to scan one by one
and you can
see it's pretty fast and I don't have to
do anything else and as soon as my order
is complete it basically notifies me
that I have fulfilled the order and the
lines are already inserted now all we
have to do is post this sales order and
we are good to
go so now let's look how it looks like
in the code so the first part is to
Define this ex extended data type
barcode and as soon as you define this
extended data type the the uh the mobile
devices automatically uh recognize this
as a barcode uh field and they will
place this barcode icon in front of it
and that's it and the second part uh
that we have used in the item tracking
uh Pages where we have manually uh
triggered the camera scanning
functionality uh these are the few steps
that you have to do inside your Al code
the first step is to Define your barcode
scanning provider
and then you have to in Step number two
you have to see if the uh the barcode
scanner provider exists so for example
if you open in a browser this will be
false and once you uh once uh the and
once the camera barcod provider exists
then you just create it and then uh the
final step is to actually call the
camera action so this this step four
could be inside some action so once you
call this there are two triggers that
could uh happen either it's a successful
uh uh barcode scanning then you will
come inside this barcode available uh
function and then you will you can do
the post-processing or if there's a
failure to scan the barcode or you exit
then you come inside this barcod failure
function uh trigger and this is how we
have used in the item tracking as well
you can see when I press the scan
multiple action I triggered the camera
uh scanner provider so that the the
camera is triggered and I can do the
continuous scanning so yeah uh that's
all from my end and I will let Gloria to
explain a bit more about the parkour
functionality that we have yeah thanks
Kim really nice demos by the way as my
colleagues has show showed you we have
integrated the first two scenarios that
we conceived for the camera Barone
scanning for the mobile application but
we also came up with a third scenario
and that is to actually support uh
integration with dedicated barcode
scanning device devices such as the one
that I'm actually Hing holding in my
hand um this new scenario this third
scenario is actually tailored and um
targeted specifically for warehouse
employees who are actually used to scan
multiple items in a span of a few
seconds and in order to actually use
this new
capability an Al developer needs to
explicitly instruct the BC app to start
listening for any incoming barcodes and
once the application is doing that
then um it's just going to start
listening for any numbers of incoming
barong data so as a warehouse employee
keeps on scanning each item in the
warehouse BC will intercept all these
messages coming from the barcode
scanner um yet again as in the second
scenario this is done via Al
extensions and it's set up per page
meaning that multiple providers can be
registered so there is multiple Pages
can actually listen to incoming barcodes
however there's a small caveat we only
send the information to the topmost page
that is the current page that the user
sees and now in terms of code I would
like to show you how easy and um
seemlessly it's we are able to integrate
the new
capability as you can see we try to keep
the same API for both the camera barcod
scanner but also for the barcod scanner
provider of of course the naming of the
methods that you need to call is going
to be different than the classes however
we try to kind of keep it in Al line
uniform NPI so it's actually easier for
the AL developer to um integrate these
new capabilities so therefore as in the
previous example in step one all you
need to do is to specify the capability
that you want in this case the barcod SK
provider check if is actually available
create the provider and request for the
barcode scanner
once this is done uh the page is going
to start listening to or the mobile app
is going to start listening for any
incoming bar code data and of course as
soon as the user starts actually
scanning some items uh we are going to
intercept this message and send it to Al
and that can be received via this
trigger barcode received and as soon as
a message is received Al can receive it
will receive it as well for further
processing yeah so that's it in terms of
the new capabilities for bar barcode
scanning the first scenario is the the
possibility to add a UI action UI button
on any client page second scenario is to
allow Al developers to easily integrate
and access camera barcode scanning
capabilities and the third scenario is
integrating with dedicated barcode
scanning device again it's really
important to mention that this is only
supported in the latest version of the
mobile app that is version
4.0 and also is only supported in the
new business Central release wave
two as you can see we have added some
functionality for the for the camera
barcod scanning but also for the
dedicated barcode scanning however we
are always looking forward to receive
some new ideas and questions from our
partners so please do reach us on all
the different media
channels that's all for what is new in
the mobile application thank you for
joining the session and thank you kasim
for showing us the demo yeah thank
you